Guide to the William Dowdell Denson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Dowdell Denson papers
1918-2004
1945-1948
MS 1832
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
15
The collection includes correspondence, clippings, trial transcripts, notebooks, audiovisual materials, and other documents relating to four World War II war crimes trials in Germany and William Dowdell Denson, chief prosecutor at those trials.
Denson, William D. (William Dowdell)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Constance Denson, 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiotape and videotape, as well as preservation masters and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers needing to consult the original materials should refer to the finding aid for policies governing reproduction for access.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Personal, 1934-2004. II. Trials, 1945-2001. III. World War II, 1941-2001. IV. Books and Printed Materials by Others, 1934-2002. V. Audiovisual Materials, 1918-2004.
Scope and Contents
The majority of the William Dowdell Denson Papers relate to the four war crimes trials in which Denson served as chief prosecutor. The Denson papers do not contain a significant amount of information about Denson's personal life. Transcripts of the war crimes trials duplicate materials held at the National Archives and therefore, the more interesting materials are the notebooks, correspondence, and photographs from the trials.
Author Joshua Greene used the Denson Papers in researching his book, Justice at Dachau: The Trials of An American Prosecutor, prior to their arrival in Manuscripts and Archives. In Series, I, II, and III, there are folders of materials collected by Greene, identified as such, for his research on Denson and the trials. There may also be materials, obtained by Greene, in other folders throughout the collection.
Biographical / Historical
William Dowdell Denson was born into an old Southern family on May 31, 1913. His father was an established lawyer and politician in Birmingham, Alabama, where William Dowdell was born. His maternal grandfather had been on the Alabama Supreme Court and his great-grandfather was a colonel in the Confederate Army.
At his father's encouragement, Denson attended the United States Military Academy at West Point, New York. He graduated cum laude in 1934 with the degree of B.S. and was given a commission as second lieutenant in the Field Artillery of the United States Army. Denson resigned his commission in order to enter Harvard Law School and received the degree of LL.B. in 1937.
After law school, Denson returned to Birmingham, Alabama, to practice law with his father. He passed the bar examination for the state of Alabama in August 1937 and was admitted to that bar in October. He was admitted to practice in all of the Federal District Courts of Alabama in January 1938, and in October 1939, to the U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals. Between 1937 and 1942, he tried over three hundred cases.
In 1942, he was called to be captain in the United States Army. His assignment was to be an instructor in the department of law at West Point, where he taught a course in military justice. Denson was sent overseas in March 1945 to the Judge Advocate General's Department, Third United States Army. In September 1945, he was promoted to lieutenant colonel.
In October 1945, Denson became chief prosecutor of the war crimes trials to be held at the former concentration camp of Dachau in Germany. The first trial opened on November 13, 1945. Forty Nazis and collaborators were charged with participating in the atrocities committed at Dachau concentration camp. All defendants were convicted, thirty-six sentenced to death. In March 1946, Denson served in a similar capacity at the trial of sixty-one Nazis and collaborators from the Mauthausen concentration camp. Convicting all, with fifty-eight sentenced to death, Denson next took over the proceedings of Flossenbürg war crimes trial. Forty-one of the forty-five accused were convicted, with eighteen death sentences. Despite being exhausted from his trial work, Denson served as chief prosecutor against the thirty-one Nazis and collaborators from the Buchenwald concentration camp. The defendants included Ilse Koch, the wife of the commandant of the camp, infamous for her brutality to prisoners, and her alleged use of human skin in lampshades and photo albums. All were convicted, and twenty-two were sentenced to death.
Returning to the United States, Denson became head of litigation for the Atomic Energy Commission. In 1948, he read that the life imprisonment of Ilse Koch had been reduced to a mere four years, three of which had already been served. Outraged, Denson wrote to newspapers across the country and was invited to speaking engagements and interviews. A congressional committee eventually took the matter up and though her sentence could not be legally reinstated, she was tried by a German court and re-sentenced to life imprisonment. Denson began seeing Countess Constance von Francken-Sierstorpff (Huschi) again, whom he had met while in Europe. On December 31, 1949, the two were married. They raised three children: Yvonne, from Huschi's previous marriage, Olivia, and William, Jr.
For the next forty years, Denson remained quiet about his war crimes trial experiences. He worked as a lawyer at different firms, dealing especially with patents, trademarks, and copyright law. In the late 1980s, Denson became active in educating the public about Nazi atrocities and his role in bringing Nazis to justice. He continued to do so until his death on December 13, 1998.
Separated Materials
The Flossenburg trial transcripts (box 14), "Records of the United States Army War Crimes Trials, United States of America v. Friedrich Becker et al., June 12, 1946-January 22, 1947 (Microfilm, National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group 338)," transferred to the Yale University Library, Microtext Collection.
War crime trials -- Germany; War criminals -- Germany; Denson, William D. (William Dowdell); Koch, Ilse, 1906-1967; Buchenwald (Concentration camp); Dachau (Concentration camp); Flossenbürg (Concentration camp); Mauthausen (Concentration camp)
- Personal, 1934-2004; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged alphabetically by type of material, with a copy of Joshua Greene's book about Denson's war crimes trial work, Justice at Dachau: The Trials of An American Prosecutor, at the beginning, and one folder of miscellaneous material at the end. Included in the series is a small amount of biographical information, clippings about Denson, interviews, research materials, materials relating to Denson's legal practice, and materials relating to the Yugoslav war crimes trials, in which Denson was personally interested.
  There are four folders of correspondence and a significant amount of writings in the series. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and is both personal and professional in nature. Correspondence dates primarily to the period immediately following World War II and from 1990 to Denson's death in 1998. Writings comprise the majority of the series, and the majority of the writings are speeches. Speeches are arranged alphabetically by the organization or group to which Denson was speaking. Most folders include correspondence relating to the speaking engagement and the speech itself. Occasionally an outline or notes for the speech and other related materials are also included. Folders that do not contain the actual speech are noted. "'Justice in Germany.' Memories of the Chief Prosecutor" is particularly interesting because it documents Denson's sentiments and views about the trials in his own words.
  - Greene, Joshua, Justice at Dachau: Trials of An American Prosecutor, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical material
    - General, 1994, 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Military, 1934-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Joshua Greene research materials, 1998-2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings [newspaper and magazine] about Denson, 1948-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence
    - A-D, 1935-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - E-L, 1947-1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - M-P, 1945-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - R-Z and unknown/illegible, 1945-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Interviews
    - Hansen, Horace [transcript and overview of interview], 1984 June 14, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Museum of Jewish Heritage [video project-correspondence and legal documents only], 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - United States Holocaust Memorial Museum [notes and correspondence only], 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Legal practice [notes, messages, complaint, correspondence, and other documents relating to Denson's career], 1991-1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - National Archives research [including correspondence, microfilm order forms, notes, and related documents], 1984-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Writings
    - "Judgment at Dachau" [proposed book, co-authored with Peter Ross Range, including correspondence and book proposal], 1995 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "'Justice in Germany.' Memories of the Chief Prosecutor" [2 versions], 1990, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Speeches
      - Allied Veterans Council [correspondence and copies of speech], 1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Barbara Meltzer's Organization of Jewish Women [outline of speech, no speech included], undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Drew Center for Holocaust Study [correspondence, speech, and other documents given to participants of conference], 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - "High School on Long Island" [outline and speech], 1988 May (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Hofstra University [correspondence, conference pamphlets, poster, and notes], 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Meltzer, Lippe, Goldstein, Wolf, Schlissel & Sazer [correspondence, speech, and press release about award ceremony], 1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Nassau County Jewish Lawyers' Association [correspondence and speech], 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - National Jewish Law Students Conference [speech, outline of speech, correspondence, and documents given to participants of the conference], 1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - North Shore Synagogue [speech, outlines of speeches, and correspondence], 1991-1995 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Shelter Rock Jewish Center [notes, multiple versions of speech, and correspondence], 1990-1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Temple Beth-Am [speech and correspondence], 1990 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Temple Judea [speech with outline, notes, and correspondence], 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Touro Law College [multiple speeches, notes, outlines, correspondence, schedule of conference, and printed material], 1991-1998 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - United States Military Academy [multiple speeches, notes, correspondence, and publications], 1990-1995, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Young Israel of West Hempstead [two versions of speech, notes, correspondence], 1994, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Unknown location [speeches and portions of speeches], 1946 August 9, undated (Box 3, Folder 32 - 33)
  - Yugoslav war crimes trials [articles, correspondence, and United Nations reports-most from Monroe Leigh], 1992-2000 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Trials, 1945-2001; Series II
  Trials is arranged chronologically: one section for each of the war crimes trials in which Denson was chief prosecutor (Dachau, Mauthausen, Flossenbürg, and Buchenwald). The Dachau and Mauthausen trials are primarily documented through the trial transcripts. The pagination of the Dachau trial transcripts continually repeats itself, and has been given artificial part numbers I-VII to ease confusion. In addition to the transcripts, the Buchenwald materials include five folders, primarily consisting of correspondence and clippings, on the reduction of Ilse Koch's sentence from life to four years imprisonment. Within the Buchenwald trials, under "Aftermath," there are two personal letters to Denson from Edwin Katzen-Ellenbogen discussing the specifics of the case against him. These letters are of particular importance because of Denson's interest in convicting Katzen-Ellenbogen and because they are the only documentation in the papers of the sentiments of those whom Denson prosecuted. In addition to the microfilm version of the Flossenbürg trial transcripts, there are four notebooks, which were unlabeled and have been given the artificial titles of A, B, C, and D. These titles do not indicate any specific chronology or sequence. The contents have been removed from the notebooks and placed in folders. They appear to be notebooks used by the prosecution team during the trial. Notebooks B, C, and D contain information about each of the defendants (a similar notebook exists for the Buchenwald trial). Notebook A contains handwritten notes of a legal nature, apparently taken during the trial and perhaps by Denson.
  - Dachau
    - Camp images [photostats], undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Clippings [newspaper], 1945, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1945, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Printed materials, 1945-1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Witness testimony, 1945 June 19 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Writings about camp and trial by others, 1945, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Greene, Joshua, research materials [notes, publications, print-outs from Internet, correspondence], 1996-2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Trial transcripts
      - [Part I], p. 1-[Part V], p. 104, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 8 - 19)
      - [Part V], p. 105-[Part VII], p. 354 [end of trial], 1945 (Box 6, Folder 20 - 30)
  - Mauthausen
    - Aftermath
      - Clippings [newspaper], 1946 May 12, 14 (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - Printed materials and writings by others, 1945, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence, 1946 April 2, May 29 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Sworn statements and trial summary, 1945-1946, undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Trial summary, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Greene, Joshua, research materials [notes, manuscripts, print-outs from Internet, clipping], 2000, undated (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Trial transcripts
      - Pages 1-323, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 37 - 39)
      - Pages 324-1293, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 40 - 49)
      - Pages 1294-2359, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 50 - 61)
      - Pages 2360-3395, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 62 - 73)
      - Pages 3396-3512, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 74 - 75)
  - Flossenbürg
    Separated Materials
    The Flossenburg trial transcripts (box 14), "Records of the United States Army War Crimes Trials, United States of America v. Friedrich Becker et al., June 12, 1946-January 22, 1947 (Microfilm, National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group 338)," transferred to the Yale University Library, Microtext Collection.
    - Aftermath [general information], 1994 (Box 13, Folder 76)
    - Court documents
      - General [statements, notes, and official correspondence], 1946-1947, undated (Box 13, Folder 77)
      - Closing arguments [3 versions-all carbon copies], [1946] (Box 13, Folder 78)
    - Trial notebooks
      - A [with inserted notes, letters, and other documents], 1946 (Box 13, Folder 79 - 81)
      - B [including official trial correspondence], 1946 (Box 13, Folder 82)
      - C, undated (Box 13, Folder 83)
      - D [containing photographs of defendants], undated (Box 13, Folder 84 - 85)
    - Greene, Joshua research materials [notes and print-outs from internet], 2000-2001, undated (Box 13, Folder 86)
  - Buchenwald
    - Aftermath
      - Clippings [newspaper], 1945-1995 (Box 15, Folder 87)
      - Correspondence to Denson, 1947-1950 (Box 15, Folder 88)
      - Official documents, 1947 April (Box 15, Folder 89)
      - Printed material, 1947 April 11, 1962, undated (Box 15, Folder 90)
      - Reduction of Koch sentence [including correspondence, clippings, and reports], 1947-1949, undated (Box 15, Folder 91 - 92)
      - Reduction of Koch sentence [including correspondence, clippings, and reports], 1947-1949, undated (Box 16, Folder 93 - 95)
    - Court documents [statements, testimony, notes, charge sheets, case analysis, and map], 1947, undated (Box 16, Folder 96)
    - Photographs
      - Scrapbook [personalized photograph album with large photographs from the trial and descriptions], [1947] (Box 16, Folder 97)
      - Loose photographs [mostly smaller versions of photographs found in scrapbook], [1947] (Box 16, Folder 98)
    - Trial notebook [with accusations against defendants], [1947] (Box 16, Folder 99)
    - Greene, Joshua, research materials [photocopies of testimony, photocopied information about defendants and case, photocopies of correspondence, a summary of the trial and notes from a phone interview with Harry Sandsberg], 2001, undated (Box 16, Folder 100)
    - Trial transcripts
      - Pages 1-63, 231-780, 784-1075, 1077-1162, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 101 - 112)
      - Pages 1163-1843, 1866-2212, 1947 (Box 18, Folder 113 - 123)
      - Pages 2213-3051, 3053-3254, 1947 (Box 19, Folder 124 - 133)
      - Pages 3255-4335, 1947 (Box 20, Folder 134 - 144)
      - Pages 4337-5401, 1947 (Box 21, Folder 145 - 155)
      - Pages 5402-5560, 5562, 5564-5718, 1947 (Box 22, Folder 156 - 159)
  - General
    - Greene, Joshua, research materials [print-outs from Internet, correspondence, phone interviews, manuscripts, and photocopies of an affidavit], 2000-2001, undated (Box 22, Folder 160)
    - Published legal documents, 1946, 1950, 1982 (Box 22, Folder 161)
- World War II, 1944-2001; Series III
  The series is arranged alphabetically by personal name, organization name, subject, or type of material and consists of items that relate neither to Denson personally nor to the trials in which he was chief prosecutor, but to World War II in general. At the end of the series is a box of Waffen-SS memorabilia collected by Denson.
  - Aftermath: Society for the Prevention of World War III [correspondence, reprints, and publications], 1947-1948, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - American Association of Former Inmates of Concentration Camps and Other Victims of Nazi Persecution [correspondence with reprint], [1948] (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Archival collection inventories [Yeshiva University Archives inventories to Rescue Children, Inc. and Vaad Hatzala collections], 1985-1986 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence of Denson to minister of war, The Hague [autograph draft of letter], undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Clippings [newspaper and magazine], 1944-2001 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - General information [WWII chronology, encyclopedia clipping, notes, and partially copied publication], 1993-2001, undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Legal
    - General [documents relating to the Nuremburg tribunal, refugee resettlement, "Statement of E. H.," and other documents], 1941-1995, undated (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Malmedy case [testimony of Joachim Peiper], [1946] (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Nuss, Barbary (Murphy) [court secretary; correspondence, photographs, and phone interview with Joshua Greene], 1947-2000, undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Waffen-SS memorabilia
    - Arm cuffs (22) (Box 24, Folder 10 - 13)
    - Armbands (3) (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - Cloth sac (1) (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - Cloth with Nazi insignia (1) (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - Insignia (2) (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - Patches
      - Collar insignia, identified (5) (Box 24, Folder 18)
      - Collar insignia, unidentified (4) (Box 24, Folder 19)
      - Foreign volunteer armshields (4) (Box 24, Folder 20)
      - Sleeve chevrons (2) (Box 24, Folder 21)
      - Sleeve insignia (4) (Box 24, Folder 22)
    - Shoulder boards (2) (Box 24, Folder 23)
- Books and Printed Materials by Others, 1934-2002; Series IV
  The series is divided into books and printed materials. Within each group, the materials are arranged alphabetically by title. Some of the books were gifts to Denson and contain personal inscriptions (noted in brackets). At the end of the series are three yearbooks from West Point: 1934, Denson's graduation year; 1944, when Denson was an instructor; and 1984, marking the 50th anniversary of the Class of 1934, which contains a short biography of Denson.
  - Books
    - The Buchenwald Report [translated by David Hackett, with personal inscription and correspondence], 1995, 1997 December-1998 January (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Cimeti è res sans Tombeaux [by Gilbert Debrise], 1945 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Witness to Barbarism [by Horace R. Hansen], 2002 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - German Crimes in Poland, 1946 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Medical Science Abused, 1946 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Medicina Na Scest í [by František Bláha, with personal inscription], 1946 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Praha Stovžatà [by František Tvrz, with personal note and correspondence], 1946-1947 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Printed materials
    - "Bayerisches Hochland" [with reprints of photographs of pre-war Germany], undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - "Behind Barbed Wires" [photocopy of Polish publication, with Polish, English, and German writing and two sketches], undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Dimensions: A Journal of Holocaust Studies [serial-1 issue], 1995 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - "The 'Dora'-Nordhausen War Crimes Trial" [booklet], 1947 October (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - "In Memoriam: George S. Patton, Jr.", 1946 March (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - "Law for Liberation from National Socialism and Militarism", undated (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Malerische Partien aus Alt-Nürnberg [by Otto Wiegk, reprints of paintings], 1922 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - "The Nazi Record", 1945 November (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - "Organization Day. Third Anniversary. XX Corps", 1945 September 5 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - "Patton's Wheels", undated (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - "Third Army: A Brief History of Operations in Europe" [identified as Denson's], undated (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - U.S. News & World Report [serial-1 issue], 1995 April 3 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - West Point yearbooks, 1934, 1944, 1984 (Box 27, Folder 11 - 13)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1918-2004; Series V
  The Audiovisual Materials series is arranged in three sections: Photographs, Videotapes, and Audiotapes.
  Photographs span the entirety of Denson's life, but the majority are from 1945 to 1950 and are photographs of Denson, his colleagues and friends, concentration camps, witnesses, and defendants at the war crimes trials in Dachau, Germany. The first notebook, labeled "Reference file for publisher," contains low resolution duplicates of some of the photographs and descriptions corresponding to an artificially assigned photograph number. This notebook was put together by Joshua Greene, author of Justice at Dachau: The Trials of An American Prosecutor, and is a helpful guide in examining the original photographs, which are found in the first ten folders of Box 28. The other photographs are in their original eight notebooks, each with a label that roughly corresponds to its contents. Some of these photographs have descriptions.
  The audiotapes and videotapes are arranged chronologically and are primarily interviews of Denson. Of the fourteen videotapes, seven are interviews. The audiotapes are all interviews conducted by Joshua Greene and used as research for his book.
  - Photographs
    - Original photographs with artificial numbers to correspond with "Reference file for publisher", 1918-1998, undated (Box 28, Folder 1 - 10)
      General
      See also: Series V. Audiovisual Materials, 1918-2004 Folder 22
    - Nuremburg defendants, undated (Box 28, Folder 11 - 13)
    - Photocopies of army photographs, undated (Box 28, Folder 14 - 19)
    - Miscellaneous photographs, undated (Box 28, Folder 20)
    - Oversize photographs, [1934, 1945] (Box 29, Folder 21)
    - Notebooks
      - "Reference file for publisher", 1918-1998 (Box 29, Folder 22)